<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<text>
<body>

<chapterHeader>
<chapter n="8">CHAPTER VIII.</chapter>

<chapterTitle>A CHAT ABOUT CHILDREN AND THEIR CLOTHING.</chapterTitle>

  <chapterQuote>"The childhood shows the man,
  As morning shows the day."--_Milton._</chapterQuote>
</chapterHeader>

<p>as a rule, it may be concluded that their <define>raiment</define> was fashioned on
similar lines to that worn by the men and women of the country in which
they lived, and was more or less ornamented, according to their station
in life.</p>


<p>One or two biblical references enlighten us as to Eastern customs. On
the authority of St. Luke, our Saviour in infancy was wrapped in
<clothing>swaddling clothes</clothing>. "Samuel," we are told, "being a child, was girded
with a <material>linen</material> <clothing>ephod</clothing>," which appears to have been a close <clothing>robe</clothing> or <clothing>vest</clothing>
reaching from the shoulders to the loins, and confined by a <clothing>girdle</clothing>.
Considering the climate and the habits of the people, it was probably
the only garment used in summer, but in cold weather was supplemented,
we presume, by the little <clothing>coat</clothing> his mother bought him from year to year,
when she and her husband came to offer the annual sacrifice, at Shiloh,
where Eli, the High Priest, lived. A <clothing>coat</clothing> of many colours was also
presented to Joseph in his youth as a mark of Jacob's affection for the
child of his old age.</p>

<p>Greek and Roman children of the gentler sex are usually represented in
the <clothing>chiton</clothing>, or loose classical <clothing>gown</clothing>, combined with a <clothing>shawl</clothing> or <clothing>himation</clothing>
weighted at the four corners, so as to assist the wearer in adjusting
it. How to put on this garment was carefully taught as part of a girl's
education. The long end was first thrown over the left shoulder. The
front part was arranged in folds across the body, passed under the right
arm and over the left shoulder or forearm. The <clothing>girdle</clothing> sometimes
consisted of a cord, at others of metal bands, and by drawing the <clothing>chiton</clothing>
over it, a double thickness of the fabric covered the vital organs of
the body. Boys wore the <clothing>tunic</clothing> and <clothing>toga</clothing>, and the latter is supposed to
have been oblong, with the corners rounded off, so as to give a
semicircular effect. <clothing>Hats</clothing> were not commonly worn, except by the poor or
when on a journey, a fold of the <clothing>toga</clothing> or <clothing>mantle</clothing> serving for a head
covering, and <clothing>sandals</clothing> protected the feet.</p>

<p>The Egyptian labouring classes allowed their children to be nude, and
infants were unfamiliar with <clothing>swaddling clothes</clothing>. The working man and boy
had simply a <clothing>loin cloth</clothing> and <clothing>girdle</clothing>, and the girl a loose <clothing>tunic</clothing> fastened
with strings at the neck and reaching to her feet. On the other hand,
children of the upper classes in Egypt were repetitions of their elders
on a small scale. Girls wore a <material>linen</material> <clothing>skirt</clothing> embroidered in colours and
fastened with a bright <clothing>sash</clothing>, or suspended from the shoulders, and over
this a loose transparent <clothing>robe</clothing> with <clothing>long sleeves</clothing>. The male costume
consisted of a <clothing>loin cloth</clothing>, and a full <clothing>robe</clothing> with <clothing>short sleeves</clothing>, or a
<clothing>tunic</clothing>, and both sexes had elaborately curled or plaited <clothing>wigs</clothing>, as the
natural hair was only allowed to grow in times of mourning.</p>

<p>The Roman occupation of Britain left its impress for a long period on
the costume of the Anglo-Saxon race. The <clothing>long-sleeved banded tunic</clothing> was
the usual habit of the industrial classes through the <timeperiod>Middle Ages</timeperiod> and
<clothing>leg bandages</clothing> and <clothing>cross gartering</clothing> preceded <clothing>breeches</clothing>. Quite young boys
appear in this <clothing>dress</clothing>, and little girls are seen in ancient MSS. in the
<clothing>kirtle</clothing> and <clothing>gunna</clothing>, the equivalents of the modern <clothing>petticoat</clothing> and dress.
Their hair, however, was allowed to fall naturally, or was dressed with
two <clothing>pendant plaits</clothing>, and was not concealed, as was so often the case with
adult females, by means of the <clothing>head-rail</clothing>. The materials used in clothing
were to a great extent the produce of household industry. The women
servants were employed in spinning, weaving, and sewing, and ladies of
the highest rank did not <define>disdain</define> to participate in such labours. Several
articles of <clothing>dress</clothing> were derived from the tanner, who worked up his
<material>leather</material> into <clothing>shoes</clothing>, <clothing>ankle leathers</clothing>, and <material>leathern</material> <clothing>hose</clothing>. The art of
tanning skins with the <material>wool</material> or hair on, was also practised, and dyeing
was in great request, for in a rude age a love of gaudy colours is a
natural characteristic of the people. The most skilful <define>artificers</define> were
found in the religious houses, but under each landowner serfs were
trained in the mechanical arts. <material>Silk</material> was worn by the wealthy, but the
common materials for wearing apparel in this country were <material>cotton</material>, <material>linen</material>,
and <material>woollen</material>.</p>


<p>Among the Anglo-Saxons and their <define>pagan</define> ancestors the desertion of
children sometimes occurred, but as the influence of Christianity
increased, it was regarded as a crime, and a law was passed for its
repression. For fostering a foundling the State allowed 6s. the first
year; 12s. the second; and 30s. for the third year; and afterward the
foster parent was to receive a sum varying according to the appearance
of the child. Children <define>bereft</define> of their father, remained under the
mother's care, but until the eldest child became of age were subject to
the guardianship of the husband's relations. Mothers usually nursed
their own children, cradles were used, and for the first few months
their clothing was <define>swathed</define> with a bandage. In this compact form they
were more easily carried, though the constraint to which they were
subjected, probably prevented that free development of the limbs, which
we now consider so essential to health and beauty. If very poor, the
father was allowed to sell his son into slavery for seven years,
providing the consent of the child was obtained, and one ten years old
could give evidence. Until a daughter was fifteen years of age, her
father could marry her as he pleased, but afterwards had no power to do
so. A boy of fifteen could enter the <define>monastic</define> life if so disposed, and a
girl at a somewhat later period. <define>Monasteries</define> offered the best education
then procurable, and the clergy were directed to "teach youth with care,
and to draw them to some craft." Schoolboys appear to have been kept in
order, by the dread of personal <define>chastisement</define>, and great respect and
reverence was exacted by their elders.</p>


<p>In the <clothing>dress</clothing> of the Blue-coat School (Christ's Hospital), we see the
ordinary costume of boys of the Tudor period. It consisted of a long
<clothing>coat</clothing> reaching to the heels and <clothing>knee-breeches</clothing>, a striped <clothing>vest</clothing>, yellow
<clothing>stockings</clothing>, and a small round <clothing>cap</clothing> placed on the side of the head. The
<clothing>dress</clothing> of little girls may be found on various monumental <define>effigies</define>, in
which they appear like their mothers, in full <clothing>skirts</clothing>, sometimes
distended by a <clothing>fardingale</clothing>, the body imprisoned in whalebone to the hips,
a folded <clothing>ruff</clothing> encircling the neck, and their <clothing>stockings</clothing> (according to
Stubbs) were of the finest <material>yarn</material>, <material>silk</material>, <material>thread</material>, or <material>cloth</material> that could
possibly be had, of changeable colours, cunningly knit, with curiously
indented points, clocks, and open seams. The <clothing>shoes</clothing> were of black, green,
white and yellow <material>velvet</material>, or of <material>leather</material> stitched with <material>silk</material> and
embroidered with gold and silver all over the foot.</p>



<p>The paintings of Vandyck bring graphically before us the picturesque
elements of the <clothing>dress</clothing> of the <timeperiod>Stuart era</timeperiod>. There is an air of richness and
refinement about the <clothing>long skirted <material>silken</material> frocks</clothing> embellished with lace,
the <clothing>pointed collars</clothing>, and <clothing>beaver hats</clothing> with trailing <material>feathers</material> universally
worn, and the quaint <material>lace</material> <clothing>caps</clothing>, which, by a turn of fashion's wheel,
have been remodelled for the children of today.</p>


<p>At no period in the history of costume were the styles so offensive to
those with a true conception of colour and form than in the first half
of the nineteenth century. We have only to turn to the sketches of Leech
and contemporary artists to find bare necks and arms, conspicuous
<clothing>underwear</clothing>, very short <clothing>skirts</clothing> distended by a stiffened <clothing>petticoat</clothing> or
<clothing>crinoline</clothing>, white <material>cotton</material> <clothing>stockings</clothing>, <clothing>low shoes</clothing> fastened by a strap and
single button, <clothing>mushroom hats</clothing>, <clothing>aprons</clothing> and <clothing>pinafores</clothing> devoid of elegance
and grace, and the hair cut close to the head or arranged in rows of
stiff ringlets. Nor did the boys of England, in <clothing>trousers</clothing> buttoned high
on short <clothing>jackets</clothing>, or with <clothing>tunics</clothing> worn with frilled <material>linen</material> <clothing>collars</clothing> and
<material>leathern</material> <clothing>belts</clothing>, show to greater advantage. Queen Victoria inaugurated a
new system of clothing for boys, when she dressed the young Princes in
Scotch and <clothing>sailor suits</clothing>, and the wardrobes of all classes have been
considerably extended of late, by the open-air life and outdoor sports
in which every self-respecting lad indulges. Cricket, tennis, boating,
football, and cycling, all imperatively demand appropriate apparel, and
tailors now give reasonable attention to this important branch of their
business, and provide fabrics and designs suited to the needs of the
rising generation.</p>


<p>Habits of personal cleanliness and the influence of <clothing>dress</clothing> on the minds
of growing girls is hardly realized except by those directly concerned
in education. Many a sensitive child's character has been warped by the
thoughtless jeers of schoolfellows, who were quick to perceive that her
clothing was not up-to-date or of such good material as their own. On
the other hand, vanity, envy, and uncharitableness have been engendered
by foolish mothers, who have provided their daughters with inappropriate
and extravagant outfits.</p>


<p>Though many advocate uniforms with distinctive trimmings for girls'
colleges, there are drawbacks to the scheme being adopted. Such a course
would probably destroy the individuality which we all desire to see
applied to the choice of clothing, and it would leave no field for
original ideas. Children must be _trained_ to select and wear their
clothes to the best advantage, and it is folly to think that they will
do so by intuition. Some may possess naturally an artistic sense and a
keen eye for colour, but they are certainly in the minority, and
rational <clothing>dress</clothing> reformers have pushed sensible ideas to the verge of
absurdity, till now the name is almost regarded as a term of reproach.</p>


<p>How much we owe to pioneers of children's <clothing>dress</clothing> reform, and especially
to <define>Messrs</define>. Liberty, who evolved what is generally known as the æsthetic
style in <clothing>dress</clothing>. From sketches courteously placed at my disposal, I am
enabled to put before the reader examples of children's clothing which
are artistic in form, light of texture, and which in no way impede the
physical development. Those who have the care of children should
remember what a sacred charge is imposed upon them, and that their
future health mainly depends, upon the manner in which they are clothed
during the first few years of life. There must be no <clothing>tight bands</clothing>, <clothing>belts</clothing>,
or <clothing>garters</clothing> to prevent circulation and to cause organic troubles; and
where <clothing>corsets</clothing> are dispensed with, as happily they are in many cases
where growing girls are concerned, the weight of the clothing should be
borne by the shoulders, not the waist, and this is ensured by cutting
undergarments in the princess or combination forms. Many young people
suffer from being carelessly <define>shod</define>, and hideous malformations of the feet
arise in consequence, while obscure diseases of the brain can sometimes
be traced to heavy <clothing>head-gear</clothing>, and the strain of over-study. <clothing>Hats</clothing> should
be of light construction, and afford a grateful shade to the eyes, if
that far-reaching ailment of civilisation, short sight, is to be
successfully combatted; and special attention must be paid to infants,
who may often be seen in public thoroughfares with a hot sun beating
down upon them, and the nurse oblivious to the fact. The sight of a
tender infant entrusted to the care of a young woman, who has not the
glimmering of a notion of how to look after its fragile body, must fill
any right-minded person with indignation. Is it unreasonable to expect
those who undertake the charge of children to acquaint themselves with
at least an elementary knowledge of the construction and functions of
the human body? The ignorance of the average nursemaid is appalling;
and though a board school education may have acquainted her with the
mysteries of the First Book of Euclid, or the rudiments of music, the
curriculum rarely includes the simplest instruction on the healthy
training of children; and, in consequence, the high rate of infant
mortality in this country is a national disgrace.</p>

<chapterHeader>
<chaprer n="9">CHAPTER IX.</chapter>

<chaprerTitle>FANCY COSTUME OF VARIOUS PERIODS.</chapterTitle>

  <chapterQuote>"The dome, where pleasure holds her midnight reign,
  Here richly decked, admits the gorgeous train;
  Tumultuous grandeur crowds the blazing square,
  The rattling chariots clash, the torches glare."</chapterQuote>
</chapterHeader>


<p>During the Roman occupation of Britain, many sports and pastimes, with
their appropriate costumes, were introduced into this country from
Southern Europe and the East, and at a very early period <define>mummings</define> were
popular with the people. These were primitive masquerades, where the
actors, if we may judge from antique illuminations, generally mimicked
the brute creation rather than human beings. They often appeared between
the courses at banquets, and on important occasions elaborate pageants
were arranged. Ships filled with mariners were sometimes introduced, or
towers <define>garrisoned</define> with armed men, while the actors portrayed some
allegorical lesson or historical incident.</p>

<p>A well-known event intimately connected with masking was the narrow
escape from death by fire of Charles VI. of France, on January 29th,
1392. The king, with eleven of his knights, for the amusement of the
Court, dressed like savages, in tight-fitting garments of <material>linen</material> covered
with <material>flax</material>, and were dancing before the Queen and the Duchess de Berri,
when the Duc d'Orléans with a torch accidentally ignited the inflammable
costume of a masker, who was chained to four others. The Duchess
protected the King by wrapping him in the <clothing>train</clothing> of her <clothing>mantle</clothing>, but four
persons died in great agony.</p>

<p>scandalous masquerades in low ale-houses, and directed that such persons
should be whipped out of London. The Feast of Fools was one of the most
singular of these exhibitions. It somewhat resembled the Roman
Saturnalia, and was enacted at Christmas. In England the celebration of
this festival does not appear to have been attended with the same
excesses as were commonly practised on the Continent, but it was
nevertheless a season of licence, in which order and discipline were
reversed. The <define>churl</define> was elected to represent the Pope; the buffoon was
made a cardinal; and the lowest of the mob assumed for the time being
the garb of the priesthood, and took possession of churches, where they
parodied every part of the sacred service, and sang masses composed of
obscene songs.</p>

<p>Dramatic representations were so tainted by the grossness and
<define>licentiousness</define> of the age, that priests were prohibited from attending
them, till the Church introduced religious plays, founded on scriptural
incidents, and which were known as miracles and mysteries. For these the
actors were trained by the clergy, and sacred edifices and <clothing>vestments</clothing>
were placed at their disposal, to give truth and lustre to the
representations.</p>

<p>There were frequent tournaments after the Norman Invasion, and these
were patronized and encouraged by Richard C[oe]ur de Lion. From this era
they occupied a prominent place in the national institutions and
history, and afforded many opportunities for the display of picturesque
costume. Ladies on these occasions were conspicuous, and sometimes rode
in parti-coloured <clothing>tunics</clothing> with short <clothing>hoods</clothing> and <clothing>tippets</clothing> wrapped about
their heads. Their <clothing>girdles</clothing> were decorated with gold and silver, and they
carried small swords. The space marked out for the combat was surrounded
by raised seats for high-born dames, princes, and the judges of the
conflict. Knights wore their ladies' colours on their <clothing>helmets</clothing>,
emblazoned on their clothing, and on the trappings of their horses; and
throngs of troubadours, heralds, and minstrels dressed in gorgeous
attire, were present to discharge their duties, and to give importance
to the spectacle.</p>

<p>The ancient English Morris Dance, performed with other quaint usages on
the 1st of May, is supposed to be of Moorish origin. It is depicted on
an antique stained glass window at Betley, in Staffordshire. The
May-pole and the Man with the Hobby Horse (who represents a Moorish
King, and is the consort of the May Queen), occupy a prominent position.
The other characters are the Fool, the Lesser Fool, Tom the Piper, a
Spaniard, the Franklin or private gentleman, a <define>Churl</define> or peasant, the May
Queen, a Nobleman, and a Friar. The dresses were adorned with bells,
intended to sound the measure of the dancers. They were of different
sizes, and were called the fore bell, the second bell, the treble, the
tenor, and the great bell.</p>

<p>Planché, in his valuable work, the "Cyclopædia of Costume," states the
earliest illustration of a _bal costumé_ is in a MS. of the fifteenth
century, in the Ambrosian Library at Milan, and he gives a reproduction
from an old painting on wood dating from 1463, representing a dance by
torchlight at the Court of Burgundy. Each person holds a long lighted
taper, and this dance, up to the sixteenth century, was usually reserved
for wedding festivities. In England masked balls were rare before the
reign of William III., and in France they first took place during the
regency of Philip, Duke of Orleans, when the Opera House was converted
into a ball-room. Father Sebastian, a Carmelite friar, devised a means
of elevating the floor of the pit to the level of the stage, and of
lowering it at pleasure.</p>

<p>Ranelagh and Vauxhall Gardens, and Belsize House, Hampstead, were also
places of popular resort, and scenes of many entertainments during the
eighteenth century. There were pyrotechnic displays, bands of music,
frequent balls, and facilities for dinner and supper parties. The lawns
were dotted with arbours, lakes, and artificial cascades; the trees were
festooned with coloured lamps, and the costumes of those who frequented
these gatherings were elaborate and costly.</p>

<p>From the writings of Horace Walpole and others, we learn that private
open-air galas were of common occurrence among the aristocracy, and he
gives a description of a _festino_ at Northumberland House in honour of
the Marquess of Tavistock and his bride; when arches and pyramids of
lights alternately surrounded the enclosure, and festoons of lamps edged
the railings. In 1761 Her Majesty Queen Charlotte surprised her husband
on his birthday with a splendid garden party, followed by fireworks, a
cold supper of a hundred dishes, and an illuminated dessert. The Duke of
Richmond celebrated a similar occasion with a masked ball and music--the
vocal parts performed by many of the nobility, in fancy <clothing>dress</clothing>. Here,
too, there was a display of fireworks in the garden and from the river.
Almack's new Subscription and Assembly Room was opened in February,
1765, under distinguished patronage; and Gibbon mentions a masquerade at
a rival establishment, the Pantheon, which he states was above par in
magnificence, and below par in humour, and cost £5000.</p>

<p>Five o'clock was the dinner hour of fashionable people during the
eighteenth century, and three for those of lower rank. At eleven p.m.
supper was usually served, and breakfast was from nine to eleven a.m.
The House of Commons commenced sitting at two, and the Opera began at
seven.</p>

<p>request, and was used in the boxes of theatres for purposes of
concealment, and by those of questionable morals. Though the large hoop
towards the close of the eighteenth century was only worn at Court, or
in full <clothing>dress</clothing>, the pocket hoop for distending the panniers was still in
vogue. For the abolition of the Court hoop, we are indebted to George
IV., whose taste in <clothing>dress</clothing> was unimpeachable. Powder and patches
maintained their ground till 1793, when they were discarded by Queen
Charlotte and the Princesses. <clothing>Aprons</clothing> were regarded as a necessary item
of a fashionable costume up to 1750, and the watch and etui adorned the
waist, necklaces sparkled on the bosom, and bracelets were worn over
long <clothing>gloves</clothing>.</p>

<p><timeperiod>The French Revolution</timeperiod> affected masculine costume; and in 1789 were
introduced into this country the <material>muslin</material> <clothing>cravat</clothing>, in which the chin was
partially concealed, <clothing>stand-up collars</clothing>, <clothing>Hessian boots</clothing>, and round <clothing>hats</clothing> of
beaver. <clothing>Scarlet coats</clothing> were much in vogue about 1784, and an anecdote in
"The Life of Sir Astley Cooper" represents him as returning from a
dancing academy in a <clothing>scarlet coat</clothing>, a three-cocked <clothing>hat</clothing>, a black glazed
stock, <clothing>nankeen knee-breeches</clothing>, and <material>silk</material> <clothing>stockings</clothing>. This may be regarded
as the ordinary costume of a gentleman at that period.</p>

<p><clothing>Wigs</clothing> had begun to go out of fashion as early as 1763, in which year the
wigmakers petitioned King George III. to support the trade by his
example. "The hair," says Malcolm, "was dressed high on the head,
whitened with powder, and alternately plaited and turned up or queued
behind." When the hair powder tax--one guinea per annum--was enforced in
1795, thousands of heads reverted to their natural colour.</p>

<p>Some brilliant fancy <clothing>dress</clothing> balls (with a view to encouraging home trade)
have taken place during the <timeperiod>Victorian era</timeperiod>. Of the first, which was given
by the Queen and Prince Consort at Buckingham Palace in 1842, a
permanent memorial exists in two handsome volumes compiled by J. R.
Planché, containing carefully coloured illustrations of the various
<clothing>dresses</clothing>, and autograph portraits of the wearers. They form an invaluable
book of reference for those desiring accurate representations of the
costume of the period of Edward III. (1327-1377). A special feature of
this ball was a series of costume quadrilles, arranged by ladies of the
Court and others of high rank. They were danced in the following
order:--</p>

<list>
<line>French quadrille, led by H. R. H. the Duchess of Cambridge.</line>

<line>Spanish quadrille, led by the Duchess of Buccleuch.</line>

<line>German quadrille, led by the Duchess of Sutherland.</line>

<line>Crusaders' quadrille, led by the Marchioness of Londonderry.</line>

<line>Waverley quadrille, led by the Countess de la Warr.</line>

<line>Scotch quadrille, led by the Duchess of Buccleuch.</line>

<line>Cossack quadrille, led by Baroness Bremon.</line>

<line>Greek quadrille, led by the Duchess of Leinster.</line>
</list>


<p>Prince Albert, as Edward III., wore a costume copied from the <define>effigy</define> of
that king in Westminster Abbey. It consisted of a <clothing>long tunic</clothing> of gold and
blue <clothing>brocade</clothing>, reaching to the ankles. The <clothing>collar</clothing>, which fitted close
round the neck, was bordered with purple <material>velvet</material>, thickly studded with
<material>jewels</material>. The <clothing>tunic</clothing>, which had an opening up the centre to the height of
the knee, was bordered and enriched with <material>jewels</material> to correspond with the
<clothing>collar</clothing>, as were the <clothing>wristbands</clothing>. The <clothing>hose</clothing> were scarlet, also the <clothing>shoes</clothing>,
which were embroidered with gold. Over the <clothing>tunic</clothing>, His Royal Highness
wore a <clothing>mantle</clothing> reaching to the heels, composed of the richest scarlet
<material>velvet</material>, bordered by a broad gold figured lace, set on each side with
large <material>pearls</material>. It was lined with <material>ermine</material>, and connected across the breast
by a band of purple <material>velvet</material>, studded with <material>diamonds</material>, <material>rubies</material>, and <material>emeralds</material>,
and in the centre was a <material>turquoise</material> of immense size and perfect colour.
The band was fastened to the <clothing>mantle</clothing> on either side by a massive gold
<clothing>ornament</clothing> enriched with precious <material>stones</material>.</p>


<p>Her Majesty the Queen as Philippa of Hainault, wife of Edward III., was
attired in a <clothing>demi-trained skirt</clothing> of crimson <material>velvet</material>, edged with <material>miniver</material>.
Over this was worn a <clothing>surcoat</clothing> of blue and gold <clothing>brocade</clothing>, trimmed with <material>fur</material>
to match, and embellished with a <clothing>stomacher</clothing> of <material>jewels</material> valued at £60,000.
The other portions of the costume were also studded with <material>jewels</material>. The
<clothing>mantle</clothing> was of gold <clothing>brocade</clothing>, with a floral design in silver. The hair was
encased in a gold <clothing>net</clothing>, enriched with precious <material>stones</material>, and was surmounted
by a <clothing>crown</clothing>.</p>

<p>Princess Augusta of Cambridge personated Princess Claude, daughter of
Anne of Bretagne, Queen of France. Her <clothing>dress</clothing> of silver tissue was
bordered with <material>ermine</material>, and the <clothing>tunic</clothing> was of light blue <material>velvet</material>, worked
with the fleur-de-lis in silver. The <clothing>low bodice</clothing> was bordered with
<material>diamonds</material>. The <clothing>sleeves</clothing> of silver tissue reached to the wrist, and were
trimmed with rows of <material>pearls</material>. The <clothing>gloves</clothing> were jewelled, and a white <material>tulle</material>
veil with silver embroideries depended from a <material>turquoise</material> and <material>pearl</material>
<clothing>diadem</clothing>. By Her Majesty's command, her own <clothing>dress</clothing>, that of Prince Consort,
and most of the costumes worn at this ball, were manufactured by the
<material>silk</material>-weavers of Spitalfields.</p>

<p>For the second royal ball in June, 1845, the period of George II.
(1727-1760) was selected, and 1200 guests were invited. The Queen looked
extremely well in powder, and her <clothing>dress</clothing> is described as of <material>cloth</material> of gold
and <material>cloth</material> of silver, with daisies and poppies worked in <material>silk</material>, and shaded
in natural colours. The trimmings and ruffles of exquisite point
lace--had belonged to Queen Charlotte--and the <clothing>stomacher</clothing> was trimmed
with <material>lace</material> and <material>jewels</material>. The sacque was ornamented with <material>ribbons</material>, caught
with <material>diamonds</material>. On the <clothing>powdered coiffure</clothing> was a diamond <clothing>crown</clothing>; Her
Majesty's white <clothing>shoes</clothing> had red rosettes with <material>diamond</material> centres, and she
wore the star and <material>ribbon</material> of the Order of the Garter. Prince Albert had a
costume of the same period, with the Star of the Garter, and the Order
of the Golden Fleece in brilliants. The Marchioness of Douro, the Duke
of Wellington's daughter-in-law, was the acknowledged belle of this
ball, and wore £60,000 worth of <material>diamonds</material>. Miss--now the
Baroness--Burdett Coutts was also present, her <clothing>dress</clothing> trimmed with <material>jewels</material>
once the property of Marie Antoinette.</p>

<p>In 1871 the Princess of Wales attended the Waverley Ball at Willis'
Rooms, with several other members of the Royal Family, and was much
admired in the character of the ill-fated Mary Stuart. On July 22nd,
1874, a fancy <clothing>dress</clothing> ball was given by their Royal Highnesses the Prince
and Princess of Wales at Marlborough House, for which some beautiful
costumes were prepared. The Princess wore a handsome <clothing>Venetian dress</clothing>, and
danced in the first quadrille with the present Duke of Devonshire. The
Prince in a Cavalier costume opened the ball with the late Duchess of
Sutherland. The chief costume quadrilles on this occasion were the
Venetian, the Vandyck, Characters in Fairy Tales, and a Pack of Cards.</p>

<p>Another historic _bal costumé_ was given in February, 1895, at Warwick
Castle, by the Earl and Countess of Warwick. No more fitting background
for such a function can be imagined than this stately mansion, which has
been a centre of hospitality for countless generations, but has never
been presided over by no more gracious and popular châtelaine than the
present Countess. Lady Warwick looked very beautiful as Marie Antoinette
(the consort of Louis XVI. of France) in a <clothing>petticoat</clothing> and <clothing>corsage</clothing> of
exquisite English <clothing>brocade</clothing>, with a design of shaded roses, enriched with
gold <material>thread</material> on a <material>pearl</material>-coloured ground. The train of royal blue <material>velvet</material>,
embroidered in gold <material>thread</material> with the fleur-de-lis, was attached to the
shoulders by a band of <material>diamonds</material>; and the Warwick <material>jewels</material>, <material>diamond</material> stars,
were arranged on the <clothing>corsage</clothing> veiled with gold flecked <material>gauze</material>, which was
also employed for the <clothing>puffed sleeves</clothing>. Her elaborate white <clothing>coiffure</clothing> was
surmounted by a white <material>muslin</material> <clothing>cap</clothing> edged with blue <material>velvet</material> and adorned with
<material>diamond</material> <clothing>aigrettes</clothing> and <material>plumes</material> of pink, white, and blue <material>feathers</material>. Lady
Marjorie Greville (the only daughter of Lord and Lady Warwick) with Miss
Hamilton acted as <clothing>train</clothing>-bearers. They wore the daintiest white costumes
of the period, composed of <material>broché silk</material>, with fichus of white <material>chiffon</material>,
and <material>silk</material> <clothing>hats</clothing> trimmed with <material>feathers</material>. Each carried a long <clothing>crook</clothing> tied with
white <material>ribbons</material> and bunches of flowers, and the effect was charming. The
Earl of Warwick wore a French Court costume, the <clothing>coat</clothing> of ruby <material>velvet</material>
profusely trimmed with gold lace, white <material>cloth</material> cuffs, and revers. The
long white kerseymere <clothing>waistcoat</clothing> was braided in gold, and the white
<clothing>knee-breeches</clothing> and <clothing>low shoes</clothing> were ornamented with <material>diamond</material> buckles. The
Earl's <clothing>wig</clothing>, _a la mousquetaire_, was tied with a bow of black <material>ribbon</material>,
and he carried a <clothing>tricorne hat</clothing> with white <material>ostrich plumes</material>, and white
<clothing>gauntlet gloves</clothing>. Lady Warwick's two sisters, the Duchess of Sutherland
and Lady Angela Forbes, represented Marie Letzinka, consort of Louis
XV., and Lady Mary Campbell. The former wore a magnificent <clothing>gown</clothing> of white
<material>satin</material> de Lyon. The <clothing>skirt</clothing> embroidered with a flight of swallows in silver
and <material>crystals</material>, a deep bertha of Point de Flandre, with ruffles of the
same on the <clothing>short sleeves</clothing>. The <clothing>train</clothing> of crimson <material>velvet</material> was embroidered
with the French emblem, and Her Grace had a <clothing>stomacher</clothing> of splendid
<material>diamonds</material>. Lady Angela Forbes' <clothing>dress<clothing> was of white <material>muslin</material>, with a blue
<clothing>sash</clothing>, and <clothing>picturesque hat</clothing> of <material>turquoise</material> <material>silk</material>, trimmed with <material>feathers</material> and
roses. Princess Henry of Pless, as la Duchesse de Polignac, had a <clothing>dress</clothing>
of rich white <material>satin</material>, the <clothing>skirt</clothing> embroidered 18in. deep, with <material>turquoises</material>
and brilliants, a <clothing>powdered wig</clothing>, and the same <material>jewels</material> in her hair. Lady
Eva Dugdale, sister to the Earl of Warwick, and lady-in-waiting to Her
Royal Highness the Duchess of York, wore a Louis Quinze white <material>satin</material>
<clothing>dress</clothing>, covered with pink roses, <clothing>corsage _en suite_</clothing> fastened with large
<material>diamond</material> <clothing>ornaments</clothing>. A silver trellis pattern was worked round the hem of
the <clothing>skirt</clothing>, and white <material>silk</material> <clothing>mittens</clothing> and <clothing>shoes</clothing> completed the costume. Lady
Rosslyn chose a white embroidered <material>muslin</material> <clothing>petticoat</clothing>, the <clothing>overdress</clothing> of
pink and red striped <material>silk</material>, fichu and ruches of black lisse, and a
<clothing>picturesque hat</clothing>. Lady Flo Sturt, as Madame la Marquise de Pompadour, was
in rich cream <material>satin</material>, with <clothing>bodice</clothing> and <clothing>sleeves</clothing> of antique lace, and
<clothing>stomacher</clothing> of <material>diamonds</material>. A black <material>satin</material> <clothing>toque</clothing>, with <clothing>aigrette</clothing> of <material>diamonds</material>,
contrasted well with the white <clothing>wig</clothing>. Count Deym, the Austrian Ambassador,
was in <clothing>English Court dress</clothing>. Prince Henry of Pless, in mousquetaire
costume, represented the Vicomte de Bragelonne. The Duke of Manchester
was in white <material>satin</material> <clothing>breeches</clothing>, <clothing>waistcoat</clothing> to match, bordered with gold, and
<clothing>coat</clothing> of white and silver <clothing>brocade</clothing> with moss roses and foliage.</p>

<p>The scene inside the Castle was one of unparalleled brilliancy, while
those who glanced from the mullioned windows saw by bright moonlight the
Avon frozen, the ancient cedars glistening with frost, and the
surrounding country wrapped in a snowy <clothing>mantle</clothing>. The entire ground floor
of the Castle was thrown open, and no pains were spared to give as
complete a representation as possible of the gorgeous fêtes which made
the Court of Marie Antoinette famous throughout Europe. The finest
spectacle presented itself when the guests assembled at supper in the
oak-lined hall, where the light of a thousand candles was reflected in
the bright steel armour which surrounded the walls. Several high
screens, hung with Beauvais tapestry and shaded by huge palms, filled
the angles of the hall, and the stone walls were partially concealed by
yellow and silver embroideries. In the huge fireplace logs crackled, and
on small round tables were placed silver candelabra with crimson shades
and floral decorations, consisting of scarlet geraniums and maiden-hair
fern. The centre table was reserved for Marie Antoinette and her Court,
and here was the choicest display of family plate, including, amongst
other valuable specimens of the goldsmith's art, a golden cup modelled
by Benvenuto Cellini. From the hall you entered the Red Drawing room,
which contains a marble table, inlaid with flowers and fruit, and
formerly the property of Marie Antoinette. Next is the Cedar
Drawing-room, used as the ball-room, on whose walls are many family
portraits and other paintings by Vandyck; the remainder of the suite of
State apartments were used as withdrawing-rooms between the dances; and
at the opposite end of the Castle is the Library, the Billiard-room, and
the Countess's lovely Louis Seize Boudoir, in ivory tints, with festoons
of delicately-shaded flowers.</p>

<p>tardy winter sun had risen ere the last carriage drove away from one of
the most successful balls of the nineteenth century.</p>

<p>Among the many important entertainments given by members of the English
aristocracy in honour of the sixtieth year of the reign of Queen
Victoria, was a Costume Ball at Devonshire House, Piccadilly, on July
2nd, 1897, when the Duke and Duchess of Devonshire received nearly all
the members of the Royal Family, many distinguished guests from the
Colonies, and members of the Corps Diplomatique. This historic mansion
was built for the third Duke of Devonshire, and it was here that
Georgiana, the beautiful Duchess of Devonshire, held her Court. It
contains a fine suite of reception rooms on the first floor; a gallery
of pictures, in which the old masters are well represented; and
extensive grounds in the rear, which on this occasion were decorated
with thousands of Chinese lanterns and fairy lamps. The principal
feature of the ball was a grand procession of the guests, headed by the
Duke and Duchess of Devonshire, the former personating Charles V. of
Germany, and the latter attired with Oriental magnificence as Zenobia,
Queen of Palmyra, in a <clothing>robe</clothing> of silver tissue wrought with <material>jewels</material>. The
<clothing>mantle</clothing> was of <material>cloth</material> of gold similarly treated, and the <clothing>bodice</clothing> was also
studded with precious <material>stones</material>. The <clothing>head-dress</clothing> consisted of white ostrich
<material>plumes</material> and a golden and jewelled <clothing>crown</clothing>, from which depended chains of
<material>pearls</material>. H.R.H. the Princess of Wales, as Margaret of Valois, was
surrounded by the ladies of her Court, their Royal Highnesses Princess
Charles of Denmark, Princess Victoria of Wales, the Duchess of Fife, and
the Duchess of York. The Princess of Wales wore a <clothing>gown</clothing> of white <material>satin</material>
wrought with silver, and a <clothing>train</clothing> of <material>cloth</material> of gold lined with silver and
superbly jewelled. H.R.H. the Prince of Wales, as Grand Master of the
Knights Hospitallers of St. John of Jerusalem and Chevalier of Malta,
wore a rich Elizabethan costume carried out in black and silver, and
bearing the white cross of the Order on one shoulder. The Duke of York
represented the Earl of Cumberland, one of Queen Elizabeth's courtiers.
Prince Charles of Denmark was a Danish student. The Duke of Connaught
wore the uniform of a military commander during the reign of Elizabeth,
and the Duchess looked charming as Queen Anne of Austria in a
picturesque <clothing>gown</clothing> with <clothing>puffed sleeves</clothing>. The Eastern Queens were
magnificently arrayed and blazing with <material>jewels</material>. Lady de Trafford was
Semiramis, Empress of Assyria, in a <clothing>dress</clothing> copied from a vase in the
British Museum. Princess Henry of Pless was Queen of Sheba, in a <clothing>robe</clothing>
and <clothing>train</clothing> of shot purple and gold tissue, elaborately embroidered with
<material>turquoises</material> and other <material>stones</material>, and wore an Assyrian jewelled <clothing>head-dress</clothing>,
decorated with a <material>diamond</material> bird and <clothing>aigrette</clothing>. Another Queen of Sheba was
Lady Cynthia Graham, and there were two Cleopatras--Lady de Grey and
Mrs. Arthur Paget. The husband of the latter accompanied her as Mark
Antony. Lady Elcho was a Byzantine Queen, Miss Muriel Wilson was Queen
Vashti, and the Countess of Dudley, as Queen Esther, wore a <clothing>dress</clothing> of
white crêpe, embroidered with gold and studded with <material>amethysts</material>,
<material>turquoises</material>, and <material>pearls</material>.</p>

<p>Elizabeth, in a <clothing>gown</clothing> copied from a picture in the National Portrait
Gallery. Her canopy was carried by four yeomen in uniforms of crimson,
black, and gold, copied from Holbein's picture of "The Field of the
<material>Cloth</material> of Gold," in the Hampton Court collection. Lord Tweedmouth was the
Earl of Leicester, in slashed <clothing>doublet</clothing> and <clothing>hose</clothing> of ruby <material>velvet</material> and <material>satin</material>,
enriched with gold embroidery. Lady Edmondstone, as Mary Queen of Scots,
wore a <clothing>dress</clothing> of pale blue <material>velvet</material>, and <material>tulle</material> veil <clothing>head-dress</clothing> and <clothing>ruff</clothing>
worked with <material>pearls</material>. She was attended by the Duchess of Hamilton, dressed
in the character of Mary Hamilton, the Queen's favourite maid of honour.
The Countess of Warwick, as Marie Antoinette, was beautifully dressed in
a <clothing>petticoat</clothing> of rich white <material>satin</material> and a Court <clothing>gown</clothing> of English <clothing>brocade</clothing>,
with a <clothing>train</clothing> of Royal blue <material>velvet</material>. The hair was powdered, and she was
attended by four pages in white <material>satin</material> <clothing>suits</clothing> and <clothing>three-cornered hats</clothing>,
bearing over her ladyship a canopy of blue <material>velvet</material>. This group included
the Duchess of Sutherland, as Charlotte Corday in a <clothing>gown</clothing> of red _crêpe
de Chine_, a <material>muslin</material> <clothing>fichu</clothing> and <clothing>cap</clothing>, trimmed with point d'Alençon lace,
and dagger at waist. Lady Westmorland made a lovely Hebe, and Lady
Angela Forbes, as the Queen of Naples, wore an Empire <clothing>gown</clothing> of ivory
duchesse <material>satin</material>, embroidered with silver and <material>diamonds</material>, and a <clothing>train</clothing> of
lilac <material>velvet</material>, edged with jewelled embroidery and lined with <material>satin</material>. The
<clothing>head-dres</clothing>s consisted of a small jewelled <clothing>crown</clothing> and two white <material>feathers</material>.
Among many other notable costumes should be mentioned the Marchioness of
Tweedale's, as the Empress Josephine, as she appears in the Coronation
picture at the Louvre, Paris; the Marchioness of Londonderry, as the
Empress Marie Thérèse, of Austria, and the Marchioness of Zetland's, as
Queen Henrietta Maria, wife of Charles I. of England; Viscountess
Raincliffe, as the Empress Catherine II. of Russia, wore white <material>satin</material>,
and her <clothing>dress</clothing> was an exact copy of the picture in the British Museum by
Lambi. The Court <clothing>gown</clothing> of the Duchess of Portland, as Duchesse de Savoia,
who headed the Venetian procession, was composed of white <material>satin</material> veiled,
with lisse wrought with silver, partially covered by a silver cloth
<clothing>mantle</clothing>, embroidered with <material>pearls</material> and <material>diamonds</material>, and <material>diamonds</material> and <material>emeralds</material>
were introduced in the <clothing>coiffure</clothing>.</p>



<chapterHeader>
<chapter n="10">CHAPTER X</chapter>

<chapterTitle>STAGE AND FLORAL COSTUME.</chapterTitle>

                  <chapterQuote>"All the world's a stage,
  And all the men and women merely players,
  They have their exits and their entrances,
  And one man in his time plays many parts."</chapterQuote>
</chapterHeader>

<p>Garrick was one of the first of our English actors to realize how much
the success of a piece depended upon appropriate costume, and, on his
taking the management of Drury Lane Theatre in 1747, at once turned his
attention to this important branch of dramatic art. He refused to
tolerate the absurdity of a heterogeneous mixture of the foreign and
ancient modes, which had hitherto debased tragedies by representing, for
instance, Greek soldiers in <clothing>full-bottomed wigs</clothing>, and the King of an
Oriental Nation in <clothing>trunk hose</clothing>. The improvement, however, must have been
very gradual, for Garrick is said to have played the part of Macbeth ten
years later in a gold-laced <clothing>suit</clothing> of sky blue and scarlet; while Mrs.
Yates as Lady Macbeth appeared in a hooped court <clothing>petticoat</clothing> of enormous
dimensions, with tight-fitting <clothing>pointed bodice</clothing> and <clothing>elbow sleeves</clothing>, and her
powdered hair dressed over a high cushion. Garrick's <clothing>suits</clothing> for the
characters of King Lear and Hamlet also followed the fashions of the
18th century, though he played Richard III. in a fancy <clothing>dress</clothing> designed
with some regard to correctness of detail. Even during the present
century, an equally absurd anachronism may be recorded. The late Mr.
Charles Mathews made his first appearance in public, at the Theatre
Royal, Richmond, as Richmond in Richard III., wearing the <clothing>helmet</clothing> and
<clothing>jacket</clothing> of a modern light horse soldier.</p>


<p>The first pantomime or harlequinade was played in England in 1717, and
the earliest illustration of an English harlequin in the <clothing>dress</clothing> now
familiar to us, is to be found in a sketch of Bartholomew Fair, dated
1721. Of the characters of columbine, pantaloon, and clown, we have no
contemporary drawings. Of the French ballet dancers of this period there
are some carefully-executed plates in Planché's "Cyclopædia of Costume."
They are all represented in long, and sometimes in <clothing>trained skirts</clothing>. The
first example of the abbreviated <clothing>ballet skirt</clothing>, reaching to the knee, is
given in the portrait of an actress personating Le Zephyr, about the
middle of the 18th century. The peasant costume of various nations has
also been adapted to stage purposes with excellent effect.</p>

<p>The late Hon. Lewis Wingfield devoted much time to designing the stage
<clothing>dresses</clothing> of the <timeperiod>Victorian era</timeperiod>, and Madame Alias--who has also passed
away--provided the costumes in Mr. Calvert's revival of Henry VIII., and
was also responsible for dressing many of the Alhambra ballets and the
plays at London and provincial theatres. Madame Bernhardt, Miss Ellen
Terry, Mrs. Langtry, Sir Henry Irving, and the late Sir Augustus Harris
have also brought their influence, money, and taste to bear on correct
stage costume, with the result that we have had many sumptuously-dressed
revivals and new plays, which otherwise might have sunk into oblivion.
Such spectacles as are often to be seen at our leading Metropolitan
theatres and music halls, if they fail to touch the public fancy, mean
absolute and irretrievable ruin to their promoters; and when it is
remembered that many thousands are spent annually in staging theatrical
enterprises, before a single seat is booked, it will at once be seen
what enormous sums must be involved in furthering dramatic interests.
The public, who have for the last sixty years been catered for so
generously, are sometimes apt to overlook the difficulties with which
the scenic artist has to contend.</p>

<p>It would be impossible within the circumscribed limit of a single volume
to minutely describe even the most notable theatrical costumes of the
last half century, but a few of the most effective floral costumes will
be appended for the benefit of those who desire to introduce them into
various entertainments.</p>

<p>The steady patronage of Her Majesty the Queen and the Royal Family have
done much to remove any prejudices which existed against the drama, and
as a powerful auxiliary to education the stage is rapidly gaining
ground. Dull, indeed, must the theatre-goer be if he leaves without
having assimilated some valuable lesson. To Shakespeare we owe many
ideal types of womanhood, all the more precious now that some of the
weaker sex, in an insatiable desire for progress, sometimes neglect
those lesser arts which in the past proved to them a shield and buckler.
The classical and historical pieces allow us to live again in scenes
which occurred when the world was young, and convince us, though the
tastes of the people were simpler, human nature, with its passions and
aspirations, has changed but little. Who can deny the moral influence of
such plays as "The Sign of the Cross," "Hypatia," "The Daughters of
Babylon," "Virginius," or those of the Robertson school, of which
"Caste" and "Ours" are examples? A love of music is not considered a
marked trait of the English nation, yet have not Italian and comic opera
stimulated a desire for a concord of sweet sounds among all classes of
the community? Such plays as "Patience" and the "Mikado" have developed
our instinct for colour and form, and we are taught the value of
industry and restraint when we watch well-trained actors, capable of
controlling every gesture, and of charming us with their well-modulated
voices. Our lives are cheered by viewing the comic side of things, and
on our clothing and household possessions, the stage has also laid a
refining hand.</p>


<listHeader>FLORAL COSTUMES.</listHeader>

<list>
<paragraphHeader>A POPPY.</paragraphHeader>

<p>The <clothing>bodice</clothing> and <clothing>skirt</clothing> of red accordion, pleated _mousseline de soie_, the
petals of the flower and <clothing>belt</clothing> in bright red <material>silk</material>. Large <material>silk</material> poppies
appear on the shoulders and bust, and one of extra size is used for a
<clothing>head-dress</clothing>. With this costume neat black <clothing>shoes</clothing> and <material>silk</material> <clothing>stockings</clothing> should
be worn, and a palm-leaf fan covered with poppies and foliage should be
carried.</p>



<paragraphHeader>LILY OF THE VALLEY.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Corsage</clothing> and <clothing>skirt</clothing> of white pleated <material>Valenciennes lace</material> mounted on green
<material>silk</material>. A full berthe of the flowers. White <material>lace</material> <clothing>hat</clothing> entirely covered with
these blooms, and fan to correspond.</p>

<paragraphHeader>MOSS ROSE.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Gown</clothing> of pink <material>satin</material>, veiled with <material>tulle</material> and flecked with rose buds. A
ruche of moss roses at the hem of the <clothing>skirt</clothing> and on the <clothing>bodice</clothing>. A <clothing>Dolly
Varden hat</clothing> trimmed with moss roses and pink <material>ribbon</material>.</p>

<paragraphHeader>WILD ROSE.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Dress</clothing> of shot pink and white <material>satin</material>, embroidered or painted with clusters
and trails of wild roses and foliage. <clothing>Skirt</clothing> edged with full ruche of
pink <material>tulle</material> studded with roses, and <clothing>corsage</clothing> trimmed to correspond.
<clothing>_Coiffure poudré_</clothing> dressed with small basket of roses and pink <material>ribbon</material>.</p>

<paragraphHeader>WHITE ROSE.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Gown</clothing> with <clothing>Watteau train</clothing> of white <material>satin</material> edged with leaveless roses,
chains of the same flowers carried across the front of the <clothing>dress</clothing>, and
outlining the <clothing>square-cut bodice</clothing>, and <clothing>elbow sleeves</clothing>. Ruffles of lace. A
<clothing>wreath</clothing> of white roses in the powdered hair, and a <clothing>crook</clothing> decorated with
flowers and <material>ribbon</material> streamers.</p>

<paragraphHeader>SUMMER ROSES.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Gown</clothing> of cream-coloured <clothing>brocade</clothing>, with design in shaded roses and foliage,
trimmed with garland of roses of different tints embedded in <material>tulle</material>.
<clothing>Décolleté corsage</clothing> trimmed to correspond, and a damask rose worn in the
hair.</p>

<paragraphHeader>WILD FLOWERS.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Dress</clothing> of pale blue <material>satin</material>, veiled with green <material>tulle</material>. Trails of
forget-me-nots, poppies, marguerites, buttercups, and grass depending
from the <clothing>waist-belt</clothing> to edge of <clothing>skirt</clothing>, and <clothing>bodice</clothing> trimmed to correspond.
A <clothing>Leghorn hat</clothing> garnished with wild flowers, grass, and blue <material>ribbons</material>.</p>

<paragraphHeader>GARDENIA.</paragraphHeader>

<p>Greek <clothing>dress</clothing> of white crêpe de Chine, embroidered in classical design
with silver. In front diagonal trails of gardenias and their dark
foliage arranged from the right shoulder to left side of <clothing>dress</clothing>. The hair
bound with silver bands. A shower bouquet to correspond.</p>

<paragraphHeader>THE SHAMROCK.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Gown</clothing> of emerald green <material>satin</material> appliquéd with <material>velvet</material> shamrocks of a darker
shade. The <clothing>stomacher</clothing> a large trefoil in <material>emeralds</material>, and the <clothing>short sleeves</clothing>
cut to resemble the Irish emblem. <clothing>Corsage</clothing> veiled with green <material>tulle</material> strewn
with tiny shamrocks, and a <clothing>coronet</clothing> of the same in the hair.</p>

<paragraphHeader>THE THISTLE.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>High dress</clothing> of <material>eau de nil satin</material>. The <clothing>skirt</clothing> edged with a <clothing>wreath</clothing> of
thistles, which are also embroidered in a bold design on the front of
<clothing>gown</clothing> and <clothing>bodice</clothing>. <material>Satin</material> <clothing>hat</clothing> trimmed with thistles and <material>ribbon</material>, and black
staff tied with thistles and <material>ribbon streamers</material>.</p>

<paragraphHeader>DANDELION.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Gown</clothing> of yellow accordion, pleated <material>chiffon</material> finished on the <clothing>skirt</clothing> with
trails of flowers from the waist to hem of the <clothing>skirt</clothing>, interspersed with
the seed pods commonly known as blow-aways. The <clothing>bodice</clothing> of pleated
yellow <material>chiffon</material> with dandelions across the berthe and clusters on the
shoulders. A <clothing>wreath</clothing> and <clothing>aigrette</clothing> to correspond.</p>

<paragraphHeader>IRIS.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Dress</clothing> of white <material>satin</material>, veiled with mauve <material>chiffon</material>, flecked with iris
petals. Trails of mauve and white flowers tied with bows of <material>satin</material> in
alternate shades, and carried across the <clothing>skirt</clothing>. <clothing>Square cut corsage</clothing> to
correspond, and <clothing>elbow sleeves</clothing>. A <material>muslin</material> <clothing>cap</clothing> trimmed with the same
flowers. Powdered hair.</p>

<paragraphHeader>LILAC.</paragraphHeader>

<p><clothing>Gown</clothing> of cream <material>satin</material> <clothing>brocaded</clothing> with mauve and white lilac, Marie
Antoinette, white <clothing>chiffon fichu</clothing>, and <clothing>cap</clothing> trimmed with clusters of shaded
lilac and foliage. <clothing>Elbow sleeves</clothing> with <material>chiffon</material> ruffles. The white <material>satin</material>
fan painted to correspond, and caught by a flower châtelaine. The hair
dressed with the same flowers, and a twisted <clothing>scarf</clothing> of mauve and white
<material>chiffon</material>.</p>
</list>

</body>
</text>
</xml>
